なんば　むった
(南波六太)＜宇宙飛行士として
にんてい
ため
認定される為には➡
To become an astronaut,
you must be licensed to pilot a T-38 jet.
ティ　さんじゅうはち
ジェット機 Ｔ－３８の
そうじゅうしかく
操縦資格が必要だ＞
Finally, I'll get to experience the same thing Hibito did, by breaking the sound barrier...
＜資格を取れれば あの日の
ひびと
日々人のように➡
私も人生初の
マッハを体験できる＞
But I still have...
＜でも その為の道のりは➡
a long road ahead.
果てしなく 遠いような気が
していた中…＞
That was when...
えっ こっち来てるの!?
《えっ こっち来てるの!?》
Huh? You're in the States?
What? She's in the States?!
[ｹｲﾀｲ](ガッ！ガタッ！)
Huh?
もしもし!?シャロンおばちゃん！
ちょっと！
Hello? Aunt Sharon?
Hey!
[ｹｲﾀｲ](ｼｬﾛﾝ)
あ～ ごめんなさい｡
ケータイ 落としちゃった｡
Oh, I'm sorry! I dropped my phone...
あ…そう｡
Oh, really...
《ふ～ なんだビビッたぜ》
Man, that really scared me.
あさって
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)それじゃ 明後日には
ヒューストンに行くから｡
In two days, we'll be in Houston.
ええ またね｡
Yes, I'll see you then.
ん～ また落としちゃった｡
I dropped my phone again.
These days, I keep dropping things...
最近よくモノを落とすなぁ｡
こわ
ケータイ 壊れてないかな｡
I wonder if I damaged my phone.
Someone you know very well
ムッタのよく知る誰か…➡
will soon be stricken by serious illness.
誰かが近いうちに重い病気になる｡
SPACE BROTHERS
You've always been in my heart
But you don't say a thing or even smile
We've always been together
We're ignorant, but we believe
All the time I spent with you
Felt like a dream
We connected the stars and drew pictures
To our hearts' content
Let our hearts, shivering in excitement,
Use the sky as a canvas
And merge to form an everlasting image
We will now distribute materials for flight training preparation.
#63 Young Excitement
飛行訓練に備えて
今から皆さんに教材を配ります｡➡
空軍の学生が
３週間かけて習う内容を➡
Starting tomorrow, you will have three days to learn what Air Force students do in three weeks.
明日から ３日間で
覚えてもらいます｡
(ラリー)よいしょっと｡
Oof...
おっ？あ…っ なるほど｡これを
みんなに配ればいいんですね｡
Oh, I see.
Should I pass these out to everyone?
え～と どれが誰のだ？
So who gets what?
You seem confused, Mr. Nanba.
かんちが
(ビンス)勘違いしないでください｡
ミスター･ナンバ｡
Huh?
That box contains the materials for one person.
その１箱で１人分です｡
Eh?
Right, I knew that...
ですよねっ やはり！
《多い！》
It's a ton.
新人は皆 この時期
覚えるべき知識量の多さに➡
This is when rookies usually start getting
overwhelmed by the amount of information.
パンク寸前になる｡
俺も かつてはそうだった｡➡
I was once in your shoes.
消火器から大量の水を
飲まされるようなもんだ｡
It's like drinking water straight from a fire hydrant.
⦅ボッ バフゥ！⦆
キツイぜェ？
Very painful.
ナンバ君には わかるかい？
消火器から水を飲む気持ち｡
Nanba, do you know how drinking water from a fire hydrant feels?
い いや…｡
N-No...
《消化剤を ぶっかけられた
気持ちならわかりますが…》
But I know how it feels to be sprayed with a fire extinguisher.
(ケンジ)《この量を３日でか…》
We have to learn all this in three days?
明日から３日間の授業ののち
５日目に筆記テストだ｡➡
Starting tomorrow, you'll have three days of class, followed by a written test.
The results will determine your order of priority for upcoming T-38 training.
テストの結果によっては
今後のＴ－３８訓練における➡
ゆうせん
各種優先順位が決まってくる｡
つまり ここで気を抜く者は➡
In other words, people who slack now will only fall further behind.
どんどん 取り残されていきます｡
以上｡
That's all.
A t-test, huh?
《テ テストか…｡➡
After everything I've been through, I need to take another test?
ここへきて またテスト勉強
することになるとは…｡➡
I-In any case, I should follow Nitta's advice.
なんにせよ
前に新田の言った通り➡
Aim for the top whenever they try to rank us.
順位のつくものなら
ねら
常にトップを狙わねえと！》
(ﾓﾘｿﾝ)この２日間の
プレゼン会議を終えて➡
After two days of presentations,
we are most intrigued by the radio telescope your group proposes.
シャロン博士の
グループが提案した➡
電波望遠鏡の計画が
一番 興味深いと感じました｡
(田村)《わあ スゴイ！
わくせいけいけいせいろん
惑星系形成論の➡
Wow, planet formation theorist Dr. Morrison came over to speak to us.
モリソン博士が
話しかけてきた！》
(ﾓﾘｿﾝ)あっと 申し遅れました｡➡
Oh, I forgot to introduce myself.
I'm from the University of Hawaii's Institute for Astronomy.
わたくし ハワイ大学で
天文やっとります｡
I am Daniel Morrison.
ダニエル･モリソンです｡
よく 存じ上げております｡
I know you very well.
(助手)さっすがァ 有名人っスね｡
モリソン博士｡
Yep, you're too famous, Dr. Morrison.
だま
お前は黙っちょれい！
You, shut up!
I believe that you've previously worked on asteroids, Dr. Sharon.
シャロン博士は 小惑星のことにも
触れておられましたね｡
そこがまた
惹かれた部分でもあります｡
That also caught my attention.
あなたと同じ｢シャロン｣という
名の小惑星をご存知ですか？
Did you know there's an asteroid that shares your name?
ええ｡天文学者の夫が
私の名を付けてくれたものです｡
Yes.
My husband was the astronomer who named that asteroid.
A-ha! Just as I thought!
ひゃ～っ！やっぱり そうですか！
私も昔は 観測が専門でしてね｡
I used to be a stargazer myself.
We all think alike.
お互いやる事は同じですな｡
私も発見した小惑星に
妻の名を…シノーラと｡
I named the asteroid I discovered after my wife.
Sinora.
すてき
素敵！
That's lovely.
りょういき
｢小惑星なんて小さな領域ばかり
見ていても仕方がない｣➡
Many academics believe that scanning limited areas of space
なんてことを言う学者も
多数おりますけどな｡
for asteroids is a waste of time.
私は…２年前に
妻を亡くしてから➡
But after losing my wife two years ago, I've been wanting a clear image of this asteroid.
どうしても この小惑星の鮮明な
姿を見たいと思ってるんです｡
《私と同じ》
I feel the same way.
とても個人的な理由なので
ナイショですけどね｡
It's a rather selfish motive, so keep it a secret.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)確かに とても個人的で➡
I agree that, as a motive, it's selfish.
とても素敵な理由です｡
But it's also very beautiful.
知りませんでした｡ボクにも
ナイショの話を なぜこの人に？
It's news to me.
Why tell her something you hid from me?
お前は黙っちょれて！
You, shut up!
それにしても
本当によかったですね｡
It's great to have Dr. Morrison backing us.
モリソン博士が
味方についてくれるなんて｡
Yes.
⦅月面電波望遠鏡の計画➡
Your proposal to construct a radio telescope on the moon
反対派も まだ いましたが…｡➡
was met with some resistance.
なんとかしましょう｡ぜひ 我々も
協力させていただきますよ⦆
But I think it can work.
We will offer what assistance we can.
個人の願いが集まって みんなの
夢って呼べるようになったら➡
When enough individuals share a common dream,
かな
それはきっと叶うわ｡
it will come true.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)すみません 水ください｡
Excuse me.
May I get some water?
(ＣＡ)ＯＫ！
Okay.
どうぞ｡
ありがとう｡
Here you go.
Thank you.
(ＣＡ)あらら 大変！
Oh, no...
How silly of me.
わあ～ やっちゃった｡
大丈夫？お客さん｡
Are you all right, ma'am?
ごめんなさい｡
Sorry about that.
Is something wrong, Dr. Sharon?
せ…先生 どうしたんですか？
水 こぼしただけよ｡
I only spilled some water.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)なんだかまた
手の力が抜けちゃって…｡
My hand just went limp...
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)時差ボケね｡
Must be jet lag.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)大人４枚｡
Four adults.
(田村)わあ～！
(男性助手)ほお～｡
なんか ワクワクするわね｡
I'm so excited.
シャロンおばちゃん！
Aunt Sharon!
Welcome to Houston.
ようこそ ヒューストンへ！
ヒビト！
Hibito!
It's been too long.
久しぶり｡
Yes.
We finally meet again!
やっと会えたわね｡
Yeah.
(少年)うわぁ～！
Watch it...
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)地球に戻ってから
調子はどう ヒビト？
Since returning to Earth, how have you been, Hibito?
I feel a little out of it.
ちょっと だるい感じかな
すぐに眠くなるし｡
I'm always falling asleep.
Ah, sounds similar to my jet lag.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)そっか｡私の時差ボケと
しょうじょう
似たような症状ね｡
だつりょくかん
なんか体中 脱力感｡
My body feels weak.
《時差ボケなんだ…》
Jet lag...
ムッちゃんには 夜に会えるよ｡
今 エーリントン飛行場で➡
Later tonight, we'll see Mu.
He's at Ellington right now, studying to become a pilot.
ジェット機の操縦法を
もう
猛勉強してんだ｡
そ～なの｡
忙しい時に来ちゃったわね｡
Oh...
I seem to have come at a busy time.
(男性助手)シャロン先生 僕達
アイマックス
あっちのＩＭＡＸ➡
Dr. Sharon, do you mind if we go to the IMAX theater over there?
見てきていいですか？
ええ どうぞ｡
No, go ahead.
うわぁ～！
ﾗｲﾄｾｰﾊﾞｰ当たったら死ねよっ！
You're supposed to die if you're hit with the light saber!
うわぁ～！
早く！
Hurry up!
I'll go order our food.
いいわよ 私 注文しとくから｡
席で待っといて｡
Find a table.
Are you sure about this?
大丈夫ですか 先生？
大丈夫よ 今度はこぼさないように
しっかり腕の力 入れるから｡
Don't worry.
I'll hold on tight, so I don't drop anything.
何か あったの？
なんか最近 先生➡
Is something wrong?
Lately, Sharon's been frequently falling over and dropping things.
よく つまずいたり
物落としたりするから…｡
When we shook hands,
《さっきのシャロンの手
全然 力が入ってなかったな》
Sharon's was almost limp.
Take this, alien!
(少年)くらえ エイリアン！
(少年)やだやだ やめてって！
Hey, stop it!
(少年)やられろよ！
(少年)やだよ！
No!
(少年)フォースを身に付けた
俺様だ！負けるかよ！
You can't beat me!
(少年)何～!!
(少年)ほらっ！えいっ！
(少年)ほら 早くしろ！
(少年)やだ～もう！
Come on, just die!
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)おっと…｡
Oops.
(女性)キャアア～～!!
(ｼｬﾛﾝの声)子供の頃…➡
"When I was a child,
プラネタリウムでしか
見たことがないような➡
I saw a sky full of stars that I'd previously only seen in planetariums.
まんてん
満天の星に出会った時➡
私の心臓がドキドキと
鳴っている音が聞こえました｡
I could hear my heart pounding in my chest.
のぞ
初めて望遠鏡を覗いて➡
The first time I looked through a telescope and saw Saturn's rings,
どせい
土星の環が見えた時も
同じようにドキドキしました｡➡
I experienced the same excitement.
私が夢だった天文学者に
なれたのは きっと➡
I achieved my dream of becoming an astronomer
若き日の
ドキドキを信じたからです｡
because of the excitement I felt in my youth."
ご…ごめんなさい｡
おばさん｡
I-I'm sorry, ma'am.
今のは ぶつかった
お前が悪いな｡
It's your fault for running into her.
私は大丈夫よ｡ガラスが
危ないから離れてなさい｡
I'm fine.
There's broken glass, so stay back.
Are you okay, Aunt Sharon?
おばちゃん！大丈夫!?
先生！
Sharon...
また こぼしちゃった｡
≪はい どいて≫
I dropped it again.
Can you move out of the way?
あっごめんなさい｡
Oh, sorry.
そうじ
あの…先生➡
Um, Sharon...
病院に行きましょう？
Let's go to the hospital.
どうして？
ケガはしてないわよ｡
Why? I'm not hurt.
いえ 体調を診てもらいに…｡
Well, I think you should get a checkup.
やだ｡
(田村)｢やだ｣って
そんな…子供みたいに｡
I won't.
Why not? Don't act like a child.
自分の体のことは 自分が一番
わかってるってもんよ｡
I'm most familiar with my own body.
じさ
これはまあ…時差ボケと
飛行機での長旅による疲労が➡
It's just jet lag and fatigue from the long flight that's throwing me off balance.
なんかこう…体のバランスを
悪くしちゃってるのよね｡
血液検査ではホルモン異常はなし
それから え～➡
Houston Medical Center
Blood tests show that your hormone levels are fine.
And the MRI doesn't indicate any sign that you're at risk for a stroke.
のうこうそく
ＭＲＩ検査でも 脳梗塞の
可能性は見られません｡
みゃくはく
(医師)体温 脈拍 心音も異常なし
…というわけで➡
Temperature, blood pressure, and heart rate are all normal.
So it's probably fatigue, as she said.
本人のおっしゃる通り
疲労でしょうな｡ご心配なく｡
Nothing to worry about.
ほら 言った通りでしょ｡
See? I told you so.
《まあ…医者が大丈夫って
言ってんなら…問題ないか…》
Well, if the doctor says she's fine,
I guess she's okay...
ウッホン！え～ みなさま｡
テストが近いにもかかわらず➡
Hello, everyone.
I realize we have a test coming up, so thank you for gathering here tonight.
本日は お集まりいただき
ありがとうございます｡
え～ まず
呼んでもいないのに➡
First, I want to apologize for my parents tagging along uninvited.
ウチの両親が付いて来たことを
深く おわびします｡
(南波母)どうも～｡
Hello!
(南波父)お久しぶり｡
Good to see everyone.
(３人)お久しぶりです！
Good to see you.
Well, there's no point in dragging this out,
まあ別に もったいつける
必要はないのですが～➡
日々人君 本人の希望もあり…｡
but Hibito requested...
(小町)もうちょい 待ってや｡
Just a little longer.
おおものふう
ちょっと｢大物風｣に登場して
もらうことになりました｡
...that we make his appearance dramatic.
日々人が希望したの？
Did Hibito really ask for this?
まさか…六太が司会して
目立ちたかっただけだろう｡
Of course not... Mutta just wanted a chance to show off.
それでは
登場してもらいましょう！➡
Let's bring him down!
日本人初のムーンウォーカー！
Japan's first moon-walker!
で 私の弟！
そして この２人の息子！➡
My little brother,
their son,
Nanba Hibito!
南波～！日々人～！
よ～…こまっちゃん…
こまっちゃん！
Koma, Koma...
Got it.
は…はいな！
イェ～イ！
Yay!
はじめまして 日々人君｡
(新田)やっと会えた｡
Nice to meet you, Hibito.
Finally...
はじめまして｡
よろしく！
Nice to meet you.
It's a pleasure.
こちらこそ！
Same here.
イェ～イ！
Yay!
(父)Ｕ･ＤＯ･Ｎ！
Udon.
Ｗｈａｔ？
Ｕ･ＤＯ･Ｎ！
What?
Udon!
お父さん
ピザ屋よ ここ！
Dear, this is a pizza parlor.
俺からも紹介します｡
シャロン博士！そして➡
I'd also like to introduce some people.
Dr. Sharon!
And the other astronomers on her team!
天文チームの みなさ～ん！
(ｼｬﾛﾝの声)私が夢だった天文学者に
なれたのは きっと➡
"I achieved my dream of becoming an astronomer,
because of the excitement I felt in my youth.
若き日の
ドキドキを信じたからです｡➡
Stars and
Humans
Kaneko
Sharon
しゅんかん
もし あなたが何かの瞬間➡
If you ever feel
おさ
たかな
抑えきれない心臓の高鳴りを
聞いたなら信じてみて下さい｡
that pounding in your chest,
follow your heart."
現在
あなたが せりかさんね？
You must be Serika.
こうえい
お…お会いできて光栄です｡
I-It's an honor to meet you...
うどんとかね…｡
There was udon.
There's space udon?
うどん あんのか？
宇宙食に｡
あるある｡つゆは こう…ちょっと
ねば
粘りけがあるんだけどさ｡
Yep, but the soup is a little sticky.
へぇ～ うどん あんだってよ｡
Eh?
They have udon.
うん…う～ん｡
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)ねえ せりかさん｡
Say, Serika?
Yes.
アドレス交換しない？
Would you like to exchange e-mail addresses?
Really? Yes, please...
いいんですか!?ぜひ！
ねえ お父さん｡➡
Hey, Dad...
何でケータイ そんな
ボロッちくなってんの？
Why is your phone all beat up?
Hmm? Oh, that?
なんか最近 よく
落としちゃうんだよな～｡➡
I keep dropping it lately...
手から すっぽり抜けちゃって…｡
It just slips out of my hand.
現在
あっ…ビックリした？
ケータイがキズだらけで｡
Oh, you noticed that my phone is scratched?
あっ いや…｡
No...
なんか よく落としちゃうのよね
最近 手に力が入んなくて…｡
I keep dropping it.
It's like I just lose all strength in my hand.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)でも 大丈夫よ｡➡
But there's nothing to worry about.
今日 医者に診てもらって…
ただの疲労だろうって｡
I saw a doctor today,
and he said that it's probably fatigue.
あの…｡
Um...
とうとつ
唐突ですが
どちらかの足の力が➡
Excuse me,
but have you ever felt that one leg was suddenly weaker?
弱く感じたり
することってあります？
Eh?
右…かな｡
Maybe with my right leg...
何？どしたの？
What? Is something wrong?
あの…シャロンさん
ちょっと失礼ですけど➡
Um, Sharon...
Excuse me, but could you show me your arm?
腕を見せてもらえますか？
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)えっ？ええ…｡
Oh? Sure...
⦅以前 診てもらったのは
普通の内科でしたよね？⦆
Was it a family doctor that examined you earlier?
(まちこ)ええ｡そこでは
ただの疲労だろうと…｡
Yes, we were told that it was just fatigue...
めず
はっしょう
(担当医)珍しい病気で発症の
確認も難しいんです｡
This is a rare disorder that's difficult to diagnose.
だんな
こんなふうに 旦那さんの
うで
腕を叩いてみて下さい｡
Try tapping your husband's arm.
(担当医)わかりましたか？
あっ はい｡
Can you tell?
Y-Yes.
それは この病気の
１つの特徴です｡
This is a symptom of the disorder.
ピクピクしてる…｡
It's twitching...
現在
ハッ！そんな…｡
No...
もう いいの？
はい｡
Is that all?
Yes...
Sharon,
シャロンさん…明日 朝から
もう一度 病院へ行きましょう｡
you should go to the hospital again in the morning.
今度は神経内科へ…｡
You should see a neurologist.
Huh?
どうこう
私も…同行します｡
I'll accompany you.
《なんだよ…!?》
What's going on?
As you place your hopes on the distant moon
And leave on your journey
You smile in spite of your loneliness
Because you believe in yourself
It doesn't matter if your wings don't match
Spread them out
As you
begin your long journey (try now) (try now)
I'm sure you can make it
Please don't hesitate
to move straight forward
You took
all your pain and sorrow (no more) (no more)
And turned it into your strength
So I'm sure even your destiny to fight many a battle
Is on your side
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#64 Piece of Cake
What's happening to Sharon?
＜シャロンの身に
何が起きてるっていうんだ!?＞
I accompany Sharon and Serika to the hospital.
＜私は シャロン せりかさんと
共に 病院へ向かう＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Piece of Cake"
I have to hurry and reach the moon first!
＜誰より早く 誰より先に
月へ行かないと！＞